<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-tei-spoken/uva-tei-spoken.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-tei-spoken/uva-tei-spoken.dtd">
]>
<TEI.2 id="wfaudio07_2">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Transcript of audio recording wfaudio07_2</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription</resp>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI P4 XML markup in conformance with the uva-tei-spoken DTD</resp>
                    <name>AEL Data</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="digital audio filename">wfaudio07_2</idno>
                <idno type="analog tape">T-122b</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <recordingStmt>
                    <recording type="audio"> </recording>
                </recordingStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person>
                    <persName id="WF">William Faulkner</persName>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <p id="Q">Unidentified participant</p>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <p id="B">Joseph Blotner</p>
                </person>
            </particDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date value="1957-04-15">15 April 1957</date>
                    <locale>Virginia Colleges Conference</locale>
                    <name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name type="city">Charlottesville, Virginia</name>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="event1">
                <head>DATE: 15 April 1957</head><head>OCCASION: Virginia Colleges Conference</head>
                <head>TAPE: T-122b</head><head>LENGTH: 30:16</head>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.1" start="00:00:01.27" end="00:00:37.34">
                    <head>Long Sentences</head>
                    <u who="WF"><inaudible/> and the long sentence is an attempt to get his past and possibly
                    his future into the instant in which he does something. But to me, what he does
                    is—is not quite as important as who he is, the fact that he is a
                    continuity, that he has come a long way, that he has endured and he is, I hope,
                    we hope, better than—than his ancestors were, that he's more
                    compassionate. He's more tolerant. We hope braver, more honest.
                    </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.2" start="00:00:40.43" end="00:01:57.48">
                    <head>Greatness and Failure</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner, a few weeks ago the Richmond papers quoted you as having
                    organized <unclear>in ascending order of excellence</unclear> <inaudible/> <unclear>American</unclear> writers
                     <inaudible/>   <unclear>you admire</unclear>. Would you be willing to suggest what the
                    criterion was, <inaudible/>?</u>
                <u who="WF">The criterion was failure. My feeling is that we all fail, that none of
                    it is as good as we all wanted it to be. None of my stuff is as good as I wanted
                    it to be. That's why I keep on writing another one, and so I
                       rated these people only by what I called the splendor of
                    the failure. The one that made the most magnificent failure I rated first,
                        <event desc="audience laughter"/> not by the—the value
                        that they did but by the splendor of the failure,
                    the—the ambition, the aspiration to do more than—than maybe
                    a human being can do, because you don't want to be better than—than
                    your—your fellow writer. You want to be as good as anybody that ever
                    did write. You want to be as good as <unclear>Dante</unclear> and Homer and Shakespeare and you can't,
                    you fail, so you write another book. If you ever did that one time, then there'd
                    be nothing left for you to do. You'd have to pick up—take up a new
                        trade.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.3" start="00:01:57.49" end="00:02:22.62">
                    <head>Jason's Lineage</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir. I'm sorry. Yes, ma'am.</u>
                <u who="Q">Well, this is more or less a question of fact. In <hi rend="italic">The
                        Sound and the Fury</hi>, was Jason Compson, did you—was he a
                    bastard?</u>
                <u who="WF">No, no, not a—not an actual one, only but—in
                    behavior. <event desc="audience laughter"/>
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.4" start="00:02:22.63" end="00:03:17.08">
                    <head>His Style</head>
                    <u who="B">Do you find that it's easier to—to write this—this wonderful
                        rolling rhetoric of yours than it is to—to
                        write a—a completely objective scene?</u>
                <u who="WF">For me, it is. I'm too busy trying to make my people come to life and
                    then I run behind them at full speed trying to keep up with them <event desc="audience laughter"/> and I put down the best I can. I don't have time
                    to—to think about style. I—I believe that anyone who spends
                    too much time on style hasn't got a great deal to say. That if you have a lot to
                    say, you don't have time to think of style. You wish you could think of style
                    and—and think of the material, too, but I don't believe that anyone
                    can.</u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.5" start="00:03:17.09" end="00:04:00.04">
                    <head>Revising</head>
                    <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner—oh, I'm sorry.</u>
                <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">In connection with that, do you revise much?</u>
                <u who="WF">I revise a great deal. I'm lazy—I don't like the—the
                    mechanics of—of getting the words onto the paper. I will put that off
                    as long as possible, so a lot of the revision is done here. Until I can't put
                    off writing anymore, then I begin to put it down, and if it's not right, then I
                    rewrite and I rewrite and I rewrite until it's the best I can do.  But I won't
                    rewrite if I can help it. I like to get it all done so the first one
                    is—will do, <unclear>because I'm lazy</unclear>.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.6" start="00:04:00.98" end="00:04:13.80">
                    <head>Most Splendid Failure</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes'm.</u>
                <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner, what do you consider your own most splendid failure, 
                    <unclear>if you could tell us</unclear><inaudible/>?</u>
                <u who="WF"><hi rend="italic">The Sound and the Fury</hi>, because I worked at it the
                    longest and the hardest.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.7" start="00:04:13.76" end="00:04:46.72">
                    <head>Writing Sound and Fury</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">In that connection, did you write it in the order in which it was
                    published?</u>
                <u who="WF">Yes.</u>
                <u who="Q">It was written in that order?</u>
                <u who="WF">Yes. I wrote the Benjy part first. That wasn't good enough, so I wrote
                    the Quentin part. That still wasn't good enough. I let Jason try it. That still
                    wasn't enough. I let Faulkner try it, and that still wasn't enough, <event desc="audience laughter"/> and so about twenty years afterwards I wrote an
                    appendix still trying to make that book what—match the
                        dream.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.8" start="00:04:47.06" end="00:05:31.33">
                    <head>Ending of Sound and Fury</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner, I once read an article in which the writer speaking of the
                    end of <hi rend="italic">The Sound and the Fury</hi>, said that the whole
                    pattern of the book does not become apparent until the very end, in the incident
                    in which Benjy begins to cry and blubber when they go left around the monument
                    and must turn to the right. Now, while I think that simply confirms everything
                    that has gone before, did you intend that as the moment of revelation?</u>
                <u who="WF">No, sir, I did not. I was still—as I've just said, I was still
                    trying to tell that story. In the first section, I hadn't told it. I had to try
                    again. I had to try three, four times.</u>
                <u who="Q">I've always been afraid it was something I missed in the ending. I'm glad
                    to have you confirm that. <unclear>Thank you.</unclear><event desc="audience laughter"/></u></div2><div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.14" start="00:10:39.34" end="00:11:20.04">
                    <head>Starting Stories</head>
                    <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner—</u>
                <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">You say you write because you have a story to tell, and you try to tell
                    it in the best way. How do you conceive these stories? Which comes first?</u>
                <u who="WF">It's the people. Suddenly people are doing something that
                    is—is tragic or funny, or something brave, 
                    of—of sacrifice that seems to me moving enough to be worth telling,
                    and then after that it's a matter of—of invention to—to
                    tell the story.</u>
                <u who="Q">Well, how do you get the basic idea? I mean—</u>
                <u who="WF">I don't know where it comes from.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.9" start="00:05:33.88" end="00:07:00.49">
                    <head>Dead Ends</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner, are you conscious of any way or theme, any attempt that you
                    have more frequently <inaudible/>, something that turned out to be a dead-end or a
                    blind alley, and then did you put that in <unclear>terms</unclear> some other
                    way?</u>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir, that's a—a matter of—of so much—as much of
                    that as possible is done up here. I have—have written three
                    manuscripts that never did quite please me, and I burned them up. But
                    it's—you try, and you try, and you try to do the best you can, to make
                    something which—which to you was—was passionate and moving,
                    so passionate and moving that it wouldn't let you alone. You had to write it.
                    And then you—you do the best you can to make it as passionate and
                    moving to anyone who reads it as it was to you, because it seems worthwhile,
                    worth doing.</u>
                <u who="Q">Why do you suppose that it didn't work out in those three books?</u>
                <u who="WF">It could be that I didn't know enough. It could be that the people were
                    not good enough people. That they—they never did—they
                    never—the books, the manuscripts, were never good enough for me to
                    pass them, so I just put them in the fire and got rid of them.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.10" start="00:07:00.85" end="00:08:46.04">
                    <head>Writing Sanctuary</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">You once disinherited <hi rend="italic">Sanctuary</hi> in the preface I
                    think to the Modern Library edition by saying it was a book written strictly for
                    money and that you hoped to make it as sensational as
                        possible If this is so, sir, why did you write a sequel
                    to it in <hi rend="italic">Requiem for a Nun</hi>?</u>
                <u who="WF">Well, I wrote that book to make a little money. I sent it to the
                    publisher, and he said, "Good, Lord, we all—we'll both be in jail if
                    we print this," <event desc="audience laughter"/> so I forgot about it. I wrote
                    two more books. They were printed. And then one day I got the galleys for
                    <hi rend="italic">Sanctuary,</hi> and I read them and it was so bad, so
                        basely conceived, that I wrote the publisher to let's
                    destroy it, and he said, "I have had the plates made. I have invested money in
                    it." At that time, he didn't have a great deal of money either, and I said,
                    "Well, it's—I can't pass it like this, so I'll rewrite it." And he said,
                    "All right, but you rewrite it then and—and I'll pay half the new plates, 
                    and you pay half the new plates," so I said "All right." So I rewrote the book and
                    made the best I could out of—out of the—the first base
                    story, and that cost me—my share of the plates was two hundred and
                    seventy dollars at a time when I didn't have two hundred and seventy dollars. I
                    got a job <unclear>passing</unclear> coal at a power plant to earn my share. The book sold. The
                    first money I was to have, sixty-five hundred dollars, and the publisher went
                    broke, and I didn't get that, which served me exactly right. <event desc="audience laughter"/>
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.11" start="00:08:47.59" end="00:09:13.34">
                    <head>Human Progress</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes,
                    sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">Sir, do you think that man is getting better and better every day in
                    every way?</u>
                <u who="WF">I think that—<event desc="audience laughter"/> I think that
                    man tries to be better than he thinks he will be. I think that that is his
                    immortality, that he wants to be better, he wants to be braver, he wants to be
                    more honest than he thinks he will be, and sometimes he's not, but then
                    suddenly, to his own astonishment, he is.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.12" start="00:09:16.83" end="00:09:48.43">
                    <head>Sanctuary and the South</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes,
                    ma'am.</u>
                <u who="Q">In reference to <hi rend="italic">Sanctuary</hi>, when you were writing
                    this, did you have in mind anything like the rape of the
                        South?  I mean, there's been a lot of talk about that. Did you have
                    that in mind when you wrote —</u>
                <u who="WF">No—</u>
                <u who="Q">Either time?</u>
                <u who="WF">No. I was simply writing a story which I thought somebody might pay some
                    money for.</u>
                <u who="Q">The first instance?</u>
                <u who="WF">Yes, and the second time I was trying to make the best I could out of
                    something that was going to cost me two hundred and seventy dollars. <event desc="audience laughter"/>
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.13" start="00:09:48.44" end="00:10:31.93">
                    <head>Writing A Fable</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">When you wrote the <hi rend="italic">Fable</hi> and moved over to a different
                     background, what did you have in mind as a bigger success
                    than you had had before in your Mississippi background?</u>
                <u who="WF">That was the only book I ever wrote from an idea, and the idea struck
                    me, who might the soldier really be under the splendid cenotaph with the eternal
                    fire burning over it. Suppose that had been Christ? Suppose he had come back and
                    had been crucified for the second time. We might not have but one more chance.
                    That came from an idea. That was the only book that was ever written from a
                    simple idea. The others have come from my own people.</u></div2>
                
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.15" start="00:11:23.42" end="00:12:49.12">
                    <head>Good People</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes,
                    sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">Young Gerald here was struck by what you said about good people and wants
                    me to ask you what you mean by good people.</u>
                <u who="WF">I mean that—that people want to be better than they are. I
                    believe that all people want to be better than they are, want to be more honest
                    and more compassionate. I think that's the only reason the human race
                    has—has lasted as long as it has, because it does want to be better
                    than it is, that individual people want to be better than they are afraid they
                    are, and they do try, and they fail, but then suddenly, when nobody expects it,
                    they are better.</u>
                <u who="Q">Then may I ask if all of these characters in <hi rend="italic">The Sound
                        and the Fury</hi>—that you would call them "good people"?</u>
                <u who="WF">I would call them tragic people. The—the good people, Dilsey,
                    the Negro woman, she was a good human being. That she held that family together
                    for not the hope of reward, but just because it was the decent and proper thing
                    to do.</u>
                <u who="Q">Jason was bad, wasn't he?</u>
                <u who="WF">Jason was bad, yes. Quentin was weak. Jason was—yes, was
                        bad.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.16" start="00:12:49.58" end="00:13:55.06">
                    <head>Human Aspirations</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, ma'am.</u>
                <u who="Q">Do you think people are good because they want to be better or because
                    <inaudible/>?</u>
                <u who="WF">Well, that can—it can be any number of personal reasons why
                    the individual wants to be better, but I think that in—in general, man
                    wants to be better than he is, that he doesn't want to be cruel, that he would
                    like to get rid of—of grief if he just knew how to, if he was just
                    wise enough. He would like to get rid of war, for instance, if he just knew how
                    or just wise enough, to get rid of greed if he just knew how.</u>
                <u who="Q">Do you think that <unclear>the amount</unclear>
                    <inaudible/>?</u>
                <u who="WF">I'm sorry. I couldn't hear.</u>
                <u who="Q">Do you think that the amount of <inaudible/> that each person has determines
                    his <unclear>ability for goodness</unclear>?</u>
                <u who="WF">Determines his behavior, yes. Not his goodness, but his behavior. His
                    goodness is—I like to believe, is a constant factor, but he can't
                    always match it, but he wants to be better than he is, than he's afraid he might
                    be, and he tries.</u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.17" start="00:13:58.52" end="00:15:31.23">
                    <head>Crucifixion Images</head>
                    <u who="Q">Sir, you indicated before that <hi rend="italic">A Fable</hi> was a
                        departure in that—insofar that it was the only book written from a—an absolute
                        idea, with—with regular city limits to it. But I find—at least, I find,
                        that the—the basic crucifixion image in <hi rend="italic">A Fable</hi> occurs over
                    and over again in your books. It occurs in <hi rend="italic">Light in
                        August</hi>. It happens in a kind of way even in—in <hi rend="italic">Sanctuary. </hi>It happens in <hi rend="italic">Requiem for a
                        Nun</hi>, certainly, with—with Nancy. Isn't <hi rend="italic">A
                        Fable</hi> simply a more positive way of approaching the problem?</u>
                <u who="WF">As a result, it might be. Remember, the writer must write out of his
                    background. He must write out of what he knows, and the Christian legend is a
                    part of—of any Christian's background, especially the background of
                    a—of a—of a country boy, a southern country boy. My life was
                    passed, my childhood, in a—a very small Mississippi town, and that was
                    a part of my background. I grew up with that. I assimilated that, took that in
                    without even knowing it. It's just—just there. It has nothing to do
                    with how much of it I might believe or disbelieve. It's just there.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.18" start="00:15:33.06" end="00:16:22.24">
                    <head>Writing and Reality</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q"><unclear>When you have</unclear> time to <inaudible/> this story, did it become
                    more—more real to you than the other things you do?</u>
                <u who="WF">Let me understand you. The story that I think of is more real than the
                    actual writing—</u>
                <u who="Q">When you're writing the story, does it—does this come a lot closer
                    to being reality than the things you do like eating breakfast or walking
                        <unclear>down the street</unclear>?</u>
                <u who="WF">At the moment, I'm completely demon-ridden to get that story written,
                    that nothing else matters. It's not that the world is not there
                    anymore. It's just that I'm too busy getting—getting my story done to
                    pay much attention to the—to the actual world, but it's still there,
                    and I go back to it.</u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.19" start="00:16:22.25" end="00:17:09.87">
                    <head>Written v Real Worlds</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                    <u who="Q">Conrad Aiken once said that after he had written a story, the story then
                    seemed perhaps more real than the things which had happened, and that as he
                    thought back on it, he felt that the thing that he had written was what had
                    happened in his life as it had, as opposed to the actual fact. Do you find that
                    so or not?</u>
                <u who="WF">No, I don't. That's Mr. Aiken's own point of view. That's not mine too
                    much. That my—my people are—are—are no more real
                    than the actual world, but no less real. That is, they have their place
                    in—in life too, to me.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.20" start="00:17:10.23" end="00:18:18.56">
                    <head>Writing v Reporting</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes,
                    sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">Is it possible that you project onto your characters a greater
                    sophistication than they have?  As I know that type of person, it seems to me that
                    they're not quite as sophisticated as—for example, the Christian myth
                    as they understand it, doesn't seem to me to be quite
                    <unclear>yours</unclear>.</u>
                <u who="WF">The writer is not a reporter. He is using his imagination, his
                    observation, his experience and, of course, his own warped ideas
                    without—not deliberately, but he can't help it. It's a part of
                    his—his background, a part of his workshop, and possibly they are more
                    sophisticated than—as I write them, than they are as they live
                    in—in the world. I—I'm still trying to tell a story. I use
                    the material which seems to me to tell the story best, and it's not any
                    deliberate intent to make these people more sophisticated than they are. It
                    seems to me—seems that is the best way to tell the story I'm trying to
                        tell.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.21" start="00:18:18.90" end="00:19:18.35">
                    <head>Help from Higher Powers</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">Back to talking about this matter of the good people, you said that
                        man wants to be better than he is and be more honest and
                    be more compassionate. Does this—in these terms, do you also mean 
                    to love more here or <unclear>is this</unclear> just another <inaudible/>?</u>
                <u who="WF">Yes, yes, you could put it that way.</u>
                <u who="Q">And man, in trying to be better than he is in this way, do you feel that
                    he can pretty much do this on his own? In other words <inaudible/></u>
                <u who="WF">Not always. Sometimes he needs help. Not always.</u>
                <u who="Q">Can he rely on a power outside, beyond himself?</u>
                <u who="WF">Sometimes, yes, but the—the will to be better than he
                    is—is—is in himself. He may not be able to do it without help from
                    outside, or from a—a greater power than he, but the—the
                    desire to be better than he is afraid he might be is inside him, inside his
                    conscience, unless he is an idiot, of course.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.22" start="00:19:18.38" end="00:20:14.87">
                    <head>As I Lay Dying</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes,  sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner, you—the book of yours which troubles me most,
                    is—puzzles me most, doesn't trouble me at all, is <hi rend="italic">As I Lay Dying</hi>. Somebody once suggested to me that the—I
                    think there's thirteen characters in it, constitute really
                    the separate parts of just one man. Is this so?</u>
                <u who="WF">No, they were—I was—I was writing about people
                    again. <event desc="audience laughter"/> I took these people, and
                    that—that's a simple <hi rend="italic">tour de force</hi>. I took this
                    family and subjected them to the two greatest catastrophes which—which
                    man can suffer—flood and fire. That's all. That was simple <hi rend="italic">tour de
                    force</hi>. That was written in six weeks without changing a word because I knew from
                    the first where that was going.</u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.23" start="00:20:16.30" end="00:21:17.36">
                    <head>Prevailing</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                    <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner, in <hi rend="italic">A Fable</hi> and in some other places,
                    you used the term "prevail" as over against the word "endure." Could you spell
                    out for <unclear>me</unclear> what sort of ultimate victory you envisioned for
                    the use of that term "prevail"?</u>
                <u who="WF">I believe that in time man will—will get rid of war, just as
                    he has got rid of—of other evils. Little children don't have to work
                    any longer. A man can no longer have his hand chopped off for stealing a loaf of
                    bread, that a—a lot has been done to—to get rid of poverty
                    and hunger and misery.  And in that way, man prevails. I—how far he can
                    go before through some of his own fault he eradicates himself from the face of
                    the earth, I don't know, but he tries to improve his condition and
                        does.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.24" start="00:21:17.20" end="00:22:08.97">
                    <head>The Sound and the Fury</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes,
                    sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner, in reference to <hi rend="italic">The Sound and the
                        Fury</hi>, again, is the "tale told by an idiot, full of sound and fury,
                    signifying nothing" applicable to Benjy as it's generally thought, or perhaps to
                    Jason?</u>
                <u who="WF">The title, of course, came from the first section, which was Benjy. I
                    thought that the story was told in Benjy's section, and the title came there. So
                    it—in that sense it does apply to Benjy rather than to anybody
                    else.</u>
                <u who="Q">I see.</u>
                <u who="WF">Though the—the more I had to work on the book,
                    the—the more elastic the title became until it covers the whole
                    family.</u>
                <u who="Q">The most "sound and the fury" seems to fall in Jason's
                    section, <unclear>in my opinion</unclear>.</u>
                <u who="WF">Yes.</u>
                <u who="Q">Thank you.</u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.25" start="00:22:08.88" end="00:23:16.84">
                    <head>Other Fictions in The Town</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">In <hi rend="italic">The Town</hi>, there are references to episodes for
                    about half a dozen of your early novels with <inaudible/> to comment on them. Do
                    they appear there simply because they <unclear>mobbed in</unclear> belonging to
                    your background or were you consciously trying to tie together and to give more
                    coherence to <hi rend="italic">The Town</hi>?</u>
                <u who="WF"><hi rend="italic">The Town </hi>is the second of a trilogy. The first
                    one was called <hi rend="italic">The Hamlet</hi>. These references are to things
                    in <hi rend="italic">The Hamlet</hi>.</u>
                <u who="Q">But there—there are references to other books than <hi rend="italic">The Hamlet</hi> 
                    that I found, including—perhaps it's simply the
                    fact that you used some of the same characters from—from the earlier
                    books.</u>
                <u who="WF">That could be it, yes. I—I used the characters which
                    are—my people to me are—are quite alive, and they move back
                    and forth through these different books, and I myself no longer remember just
                    where what character appeared. I remember that character, but I don't always
                    remember what he did. 
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.26" start="00:23:20.73" end="00:24:46.04">
                    <head>Regional v Universal</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">I would like to ask if your people are derived principally from an area
                    or region of Mississippi, and if you think that was a way of life there that has
                    more to offer than, say, if a writer <inaudible/> perhaps to—the idea is that your surroundings
                    <inaudible/> as well as your own education and your own <inaudible/>.</u>
                <u who="WF">I don't think people are that different. I think there is not a great
                    deal of difference between southerners and northerners, and Americans and
                    Russians and Chinese. That I'm simply using the—the background, the
                    color, the—the smells, the—the sounds that I am familiar
                    with, but the people in my opinion are not that different. They could be
                    anywhere. Of course they would wear different clothes, and their behavior might
                    be a little awry from what it is in north Mississippi, but the behavior would be
                    the same. They would have the same anguishes, the same hopes, and
                    they—Russians or Chinese—would still want to be better than
                    they are afraid they might be, and they would <unclear>both</unclear> try to be
                        better.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.27" start="00:24:48.61" end="00:26:10.26">
                    <head>Shocking Mississippians</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, ma'am.</u>
                <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner, you talk about your—so many of the things you
                    write about come from your background. A good part of my family is from
                        <unclear>Clarksdale</unclear>, Mississippi, and Mississippians are proud of
                    you, but you've shocked a great many of us. <event desc="audience laughter"/> I
                    wonder, do you think that stems from a reluctance on their part to see some of
                    the people you write about in their midst?</u>
                <u who="WF">Well, I don't know. There are not too many Mississippians read very much,
                    and they're probably <event desc="audience laughter"/> <inaudible/> 
                    <unclear>and they</unclear> spend as much time as I do just writing. I'm
                    sorry that I—I—I shock my—people of my own country, but I'm simply
                    trying to—to tell about people which I think are—are
                     astounding and marvelous creatures, well worth writing about
                    in the—the terms which seem to me the best to make the story vivid and
                        memorable.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.28" start="00:26:11.04" end="00:26:32.89">
                    <head>"A Rose for Emily"</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, ma'am.</u>
                <u who="Q">What is the meaning of the title "A Rose for Emily"?</u>
                <u who="WF">Oh, it's simply the poor woman had had no life at all. Her father had
                    kept her more or less locked up, and then she had a lover, and he was about to quit
                    her. She had to murder him. It was just "A Rose for Emily," that's all. <event desc="audience laughter"/></u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.29" start="00:26:32.90" end="00:27:08.05">
                    <head>Great Older Writers</head>
                    <u who="Q">Does your criterion <unclear>apply, to say, the great writers of the
                        past</unclear>
                    <inaudible/>?</u>
                <u who="WF">No'm, the—the criterion for judging the—the writing of
                    the past is the ones that I like to read, that I will read again and again and
                    again. I—I don't know of any writer of the present who—whose
                    work I will read again and again and again, as I will read Cervantes, for
                    instance, or Dickens.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.30" start="00:27:12.15" end="00:27:54.04">
                    <head>Great Modern Writers</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, ma'am.</u>
                <u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner, don't you believe that in a few hundred years, say, that
                    there will be books produced, that were produced in this century, that will be
                    read over and over again as Dickens <unclear>is read today</unclear>?</u>
                <u who="WF">Now that I can't say, for the reason that the writer is really too
                    busy with his own work to have much time to read what anybody else does, so I
                    just don't know really what people are writing today. I do—do know
                    that what I write ain't as good as I want it to be, <event desc="audience laughter"/> and so I'm going to keep on trying to write one
                    that will suit me. I probably won't, but I intend to keep on trying.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.31" start="00:27:55.04" end="00:28:49.78">
                    <head>Writing Regularly</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, ma'am.</u>
                <u who="Q">I've read and also I've heard the poet John <unclear>Neihardt</unclear> say that you have to
                    make yourself sit there and write something every day, that that's the way to do
                    it, <unclear>whether it's</unclear> <inaudible/> or not <inaudible/>.  How much is inspiration and 
                    how much is perspiration?</u>
                <u who="WF">I—that system works with lots of people, but not with me. I
                    never had any trouble writing the stuff. It's persuading myself to sit down and
                    do it. <event desc="audience laughter"/> Some people, that sort of
                     discipline works with, but—but with others,
                    it—it don't. With me, it never would, that I put off writing as long
                    as possible and then when I get started, I can write for ten or twelve hours
                    day after day until I get <inaudible/> until I get—</u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.32" start="00:28:50.60" end="00:29:29.23">
                    <head>Stories Becoming Novels</head>
                    <u who="Q">Strictly as a matter of your choice of forms, do
                    you ever find yourself beginning a short story that suddenly blossoms or has to
                    blossom into a novel, or <unclear>vice versa</unclear>?</u>
                <u who="WF"> <unclear>Yes, sir</unclear>
                </u>
                <u who="Q">Or can you cite from the novels that—</u>
                <u who="WF"><hi rend="italic">The Sound and the Fury</hi> started as a short story.
                    I thought it could be done in ten pages. Then I had written a hundred pages, and
                    that wasn't enough. I wrote another hundred. That wasn't enough. Another
                    hundred. That still wasn't enough.
                </u></div2>
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio07_2.33" start="00:29:30.12" end="00:30:13.93">
                    <head>Tennessee Williams</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes,
                    sir.</u>
                <u who="Q">Sir, a great many of the people that Tennessee Williams writes about are
                    southerners. What is your opinion of these people <unclear>that he writes
                        about</unclear>?</u>
                <u who="WF">Well, the—I couldn't have any opinion of the people that he
                    writes about. I could have an opinion of the—of the complete job
                    that's done. The best of—of Williams, to me, was a play called <hi rend="italic">Camino Real</hi>. I think <hi rend="italic">Cat on a Hot Tin
                        Roof</hi> was written about the wrong people. The story was the old man's
                    story. I think that the anguishes of children ain't worth three acts. <event desc="audience laughter"/> <event desc="end of recording"/></u></div2>
                </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>