<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-tei-spoken/uva-tei-spoken.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-tei-spoken/uva-tei-spoken.dtd">
]>
<TEI.2 id="wfaudio23_1">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Transcript of audio recording wfaudio23_1</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Creation of electronic transcription</resp>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI P4 XML markup in conformance with the uva-tei-spoken DTD</resp>
					<name>AEL Data</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
				<idno type="digital audio filename">wfaudio23_1</idno>
				<idno type="analog tape">T-142a</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<recordingStmt>
					<recording type="audio"> </recording>
				</recordingStmt>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person>
					<persName id="WF">William Faulkner</persName>
				</person>
				<person>
					<p id="M">Moderator</p>
				</person>
				<person>
					<p id="Q">Unidentified participant</p>
				</person>
				<person>
					<p id="FS">Floyd Stovall</p>
				</person>
				<person>
					<p id="JC">John Coleman</p>
				</person>
				<person>
					<persName id="B">Joseph Blotner</persName>
				</person>
				<person>
					<p id="AKD">A. K. Davis</p>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<settingDesc>
				<setting>
					<date value="1958-04-24">24 April 1958</date>
					<locale>Undergraduate Writing Class</locale>
					<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
					<name type="city">Charlottesville, Virginia</name>
				</setting>
			</settingDesc>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="event1">
				<head>DATE: 24 April 1958</head><head>OCCASION: Undergraduate Writing Class</head>
				<head>TAPE: T-142a</head><head>LENGTH: 33:46</head>
				<head>READING: "A Word to Young Writers"</head>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.1" start="00:00:04.06" end="00:00:36.06">
					<head>Faulkner's Introduction</head>
					<u who="WF">We're both given to stage fright.
					I hope we're both well enough known here by now to where we don't need too much
						introduction. Am I talking right, you think?  <event desc="audience laughter"/> This would be addressed
						to—to young writers. It's a suggestion more than a—an idea.
					</u></div2>
				<div2 type="reading" id="wfaudio23_1.2" start="00:00:36.10" end="00:01:49.09">
					<head>Speech, Excerpt 1</head>
					<u who="WF">
					<writing type="speech">Two years ago President Eisenhower conceived a plan based
						on an idea which is basically a sound one. This was that world conditions,
						the universal dilemma of mankind at this moment, are what they are simply
						because individual men and women of different races and tongues and
						conditions cannot discuss with one another these problems and dilemmas,
						which are primarily theirs, but must attempt to do so only through the
						formal organizations of their antagonistic and seemingly irreconcilable
						governments. That is, that individual people in all walks of life should be
						given opportunity to speak to their individual opposite numbers all over the
						earth—laborer to laborer, scientist to scientist, doctors and
						lawyers and merchants and bankers and artists to their opposite numbers
						everywhere. There was nothing wrong with this idea. Certainly no
						artist—painter, musician, sculptor, architect, or
						writer—would dispute it because this, trying to communicate man
						to man regardless of race or color or condition, is exactly what every
						artist has already spent all his life trying to do, and as long as he
						breathes, will continue to do.
					</writing>
					</u></div2>
				<div2 type="reading" id="wfaudio23_1.3" start="00:01:49.10" end="00:03:27.88">
					<head>Speech, Excerpt 2</head>
					<u who="WF">
					<writing type="speech">What doomed it, in my opinion, was symptomized by the
						phraseology of the President's own concept—laborer to laborer,
						artist to artist, banker to banker, tycoon to tycoon. What doomed it, in my
						opinion, was an evil inherent in our culture itself. An evil quality
						inherent in and perhaps necessary, though I do—though I, for one,
						do not believe this last, in the culture of any country capable of enduring
						and surviving through this period of history. This is the mystical belief,
						almost a religion, that individual man cannot speak to individual man
						because individual man can no longer exist. A belief that there is no place
						anymore where individual man can speak quietly to individual man of such
						simple things as honesty to oneself and responsibility toward others and
						protection for the weak and compassion and pity for all, because such
						individual things as honesty and pity and responsibility and compassion no
						longer exist, and man himself can hope to continue only by relinquishing and
						denying his individuality into a regimented group of his arbitrary,
						factional kind, arrayed against an opposite opposed arbitrary, factional,
						regimented group, both filling the same air at the same time with the same
						double-barreled abstractions of "peoples' democracy" and "minority rights"
						and "equal justice" and "social welfare"—all the synonyms which
						take all the shame out of irresponsibility by not merely inviting but even
						compelling everyone to participate in it.
					</writing>
					</u></div2>
				<div2 type="reading" id="wfaudio23_1.4" start="00:03:27.89" end="00:05:18.42">
					<head>Speech, Excerpt 3</head>
					<u who="WF">
					<writing type="speech">So, in this case—I mean the President's
						People-to-People Committee—the artist, too, who has already spent
						his life trying to communicate simply people-to-people the problems and
						passions of the human heart and how to survive them or, anyway, endure them,
						has in effect been asked by the president of his country to affirm that
						mythology which has—which he has already devoted his life to
						denying: the mythology that one single individual man is nothing, and
						can—can have weight and substance only when organized into the
						anonymity of a group where he will have surrendered his individual soul for
						a number. It would be sad enough if only at such moments as this—I
						mean, formal recognition by his country of the validity of his life's
						dedication—did the artist have to run full-tilt into what might be
						called almost a universal will to regimentation, a universal will to
						obliterate the humanity from even—from man even to the extent of
						relieving him not only of moral responsibility, but even of physical pain
						and mortality, by effacing his individuality into any—it does not matter
						which as long as he has vanished into one of them—nationally-recognized
						economic group by profession or trade or occupation or income-tax bracket
						or, if nothing else offers, finance-company list. His tragedy is that today
						he must even combat this pressure, waste some part of his puny but, if he is
						an artist, precious individual strength against this universal will to
						efface his individual humanity, in order to be an artist. Which comes at
						last to the idea I want to suggest, which is what seems to me to be the one
						dilemma in which all young writers today participate.
					</writing>
					</u></div2>
				<div2 type="reading" id="wfaudio23_1.5" start="00:05:18.43" end="00:05:49.80">
					<head>Speech, Excerpt 4</head>
					<u who="WF">
					<writing type="speech">I think that perhaps all writers, while they are hot,
						working at top speed to try to get said all they feel the terrific urgency
						to say, don't read the writers younger, after themselves. Perhaps for the
						same reason which the sprinter or the distance-runner has—he does
						not have time to be interested in who is behind him or even up with him, but
						only in who is in front. That was true in my own case, anyway, so there was
						a gap of about twenty-five years during which I had almost no acquaintance
						whatever with contemporary literature.
					</writing>
					</u></div2>
				<div2 type="reading" id="wfaudio23_1.6" start="00:05:49.76" end="00:08:17.45">
					<head>Speech, Excerpt 5</head>
					<u who="WF">
					<writing type="speech">So, when a short time ago I did begin to read the
						writing being done now, I brought to it not only ignorance but a kind of
						innocence, freshness, what you might call a point of view and an
							interest virgin of preconceptions. Anyway, I got
						from the first story an impression which has repeated itself so consistently
						since that I shall offer it as a generalization. This is, that the young
						writer of today is compelled by the present state of our culture, which I
						tried to describe, to function in a kind of vacuum of the human race. His
						characters do not function, live, breathe, struggle, in that moil and seethe
						of simple humanity as did those of our predecessors who were the masters
						from whom we learned our craft—Dickens, Fielding, Thackeray,
						Conrad, Twain, Smollett, Hawthorne, Melville, James. Their names are legion
						whose created characters were not just weaned but even spawned into a moil
						and seethe of simple human beings whose very existence was an affirmation of
						an incurable and indomitable optimism—men and women like
						our—themselves, understandable and comprehensible even when
						antipathetical, even in the very moment while they were murdering or robbing
						or betraying you, since theirs too were the same simple human lusts and
						hopes and fears uncomplicated by regimentation or group compulsion. A moil
						and seethe of humanity into which they could venture, not only unappalled
						and welcome, but with pleasure too, since with no threat of
						harm—and with no threat of harm since the worst that could happen
						to them would be a head butt by what was only another human head. An elbow
						or a knee skinned, but that too was only another human knee or elbow which
						did the skinning. A moil and seethe of mankind which accepted and believed
						in and functioned according, not to angles, but to moral principles. Where
						truth was not where you were standing when you looked at it, but was an
						unalterable quality or thing which could and would knock your brains out if
						you did not accept it or at least respect it. While today the young writer's
						characters must function not in individuality but in isolation, not to
						pursue in myriad company the anguishes and hopes of all human hearts in a
						world of a few simple, comprehensible truths and moral principles, but to
						exist alone inside a vacuum of facts which he did not choose and cannot cope
						with and cannot escape from like a fly inside an inverted tumbler.
					</writing>
					</u></div2>
				<div2 type="reading" id="wfaudio23_1.7" start="00:08:17.45" end="00:09:22.00">
					<head>Speech, Excerpt 6</head>
					<u who="WF">
					<writing type="speech">Let me repeat. I have not read all the work of this
						present generation of writing. I have not had time yet. So I must speak only
						of the ones I do know. I am thinking now of what I rate the best one,
						Salinger's <hi rend="italic">Catcher in the Rye</hi>, perhaps because this
						one expresses so completely what I have tried to say. A youth, father to
						what will—must—someday be a man, more intelligent than some and more
						sensitive than most, who—he would not even have called it by
						instinct because he did not know he possessed it because God perhaps had put
						it there, loved man and wished to be a part of mankind, humanity, who tried
						to join the human race and failed. To me, his tragedy was not that he was,
						as he perhaps thought, not tough enough or brave enough or deserving enough
						to be accepted into humanity. His tragedy was that when he attempted to
						enter the human race, there was no human race there. There was nothing for
						him to do save buzz, frantic and inviolate, inside the glass wall of his
						tumbler, until he either gave up or was himself, by himself, by his own
						frantic buzzing, destroyed.
					</writing>
					</u></div2>
				<div2 type="reading" id="wfaudio23_1.8" start="00:09:22.00" end="00:10:31.02">
					<head>Speech, Excerpt 7</head>
					<u who="WF">
					<writing type="speech">One thinks of course immediately of Huck Finn, another
						youth already father to what will some day soon now be a man. But in Huck's
						case all he had to combat was his small size, which time would cure for him.
						In time he would be as big as any man he had to cope with. And even as it
						was, all the adult world could do to harm him was to skin his nose a little.
						Humanity, the human race, would and was accepting him already. All he needed
						to do was just to grow up into it. That is the young writer's dilemma as I see
						it. Not just his, but all our problems is to save mankind from being
						de-souled as the stallion or boar or bull is gelded, to save the individual
						from anonymity before it is too late, and humanity has vanished from the
						animal called man. And who better to save man's humanity than the writer,
						the poet, the artist, since who should fear the loss of it more, since the
						humanity of man is the artist's life's blood? <event desc="applause"/></writing>
					
					</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.9" start="00:10:30.75" end="00:10:49.04">
					<head>Audience Prompt</head>
					<u who="M">Mr. Faulkner has consented
					to answer any questions you might have about this paper or about his works. So
						<unclear>who shall lead</unclear> the questions?</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.10" start="00:10:55.95" end="00:12:10.41">
					<head>Anse</head>
					<u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
				<u who="Q">In <hi rend="italic">As I Lay Dying,</hi> in the soliloquy of Addie
					Bundren, she says that when she first met Anse that he had a good farm, and that
					he was on that farm, and that he farmed it himself, and one gets the impression that
					he was doing a pretty good job of it, and yet when we see him in the book, he's
					a—a ne'er do well. He—he depends on his neighbors. I was
					wondering if there were—was any implication that Addie might have
						sapped his will to—to work or his will to be a
					personality?</u>
				<u who="WF">No, I wouldn't say so. I suspect that Anse didn't like to farm anyway,
					and he was just waiting until he could find a wife and get some children to do
					the work for him. And soon as he got some children to do the work, he quit.
					That's the sort of Anse Bundrens that I'm familiar with in my country, and I
					imagine he exists in Virginia, too. <event desc="audience laughter"/>
				</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.11" start="00:12:23.73" end="00:13:47.25">
					<head>Reason for Speech</head>
					<u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
				<u who="Q">May I ask you what moved you to write that essay? I find it very profound
					<inaudible/>.</u>
				<u who="WF">I—I reckon that—that anything you have devoted a
					great deal of your time to, any sort of craft, whether it's an important one or
					not, becomes pretty serious to you, and maybe when you get along you think,
					"Well, I have—if it's not valid, I have wasted a lot of pretty valuable
					time," and so I prefer to believe that it is valid, and it should continue, and
					the people to carry it on are the people that come after me, and if—if
					my thoughts about it are—are worth anything, whether they are or not,
					it had better be expressed so the young people after me can take a look at them
					and say, "It's nonsense," or not. I suppose that's the reason. That—no
					particular need to—to improve writing or to better man's condition
					maybe, any more than any artist has. I think maybe it's not so much to better
					man's condition but maybe to uplift his heart, to give him pleasure, fun.
					Anyway, it becomes important to the one who's spent all his life laying the
					brick, and he wants the trade of bricklaying to continue.</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.12" start="00:13:49.69" end="00:15:14.88">
					<head>Young Writers' Predicament</head>
					<u who="FS">Mr. Faulkner, do you—do you feel that this predicament of the young writer is one which he has in his
					individual resources the ability to escape from, or is he the victim of a social
					condition which he can't possibly escape?</u>
				<u who="WF">He does not need to be victim of it if he does not want to. He inherited
					this condition, and possibly he himself knows there's—something somewhere is
					wrong, but he doesn't know what. It may be someone who is old enough to have
					seen the other side of this <unclear>nettle</unclear> may be able to tell him,
					"This is where the trouble is." No, sir, I don't think that—that he's
					the victim of it. He simply inherited a condition which is not too good,
					but—but I doubt if anything can stop the artist from being an artist,
					and I doubt if any condition, economic or social or any other, is going to
					prevent the good work being done, that even without anybody to say, "This is
					what my hindsight tells me is wrong," will—will aid
					him—well, it will shorten the time maybe. He doesn't need to be told
					what's wrong. He will—will solve that problem himself if he's going to
					keep working, and the good one will keep working.
				</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.13" start="00:15:14.84" end="00:16:21.08">
					<head>Ike's Predicament</head>
					<u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
				<u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner, Isaac McCaslin in "The Bear" relinquishes his heredity. Do
					you think he may be in the same predicament as modern man, under the same
					conditions that he can't find a humanity that he can fit in with?</u>
				<u who="WF">Well, there are some people in any time and age that—that
					cannot face and cope with the problems. There seems to be three stages. The
					first says, "This is rotten. I'll have no part of it. I will—will take
					death first." The second says, "This is rotten. I don't like it. I can't do
					anything about it, but at least I will not participate in it myself. I will go
					off into a cave or—or climb a pillar to sit on." The third says, "This
					stinks, and I'm going to do something about it." McCaslin is the second. He
					says, "This is bad, and I will withdraw from it." What we need are people who
					will say, "This is bad, and I'm going to do something about it. I'm going to
					change it."
				</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.14" start="00:16:22.90" end="00:20:02.57">
					<head>Modern Poet's Status</head>
					<u who="WF"> Yes, sir.</u>
				<u who="Q">There is a great problem of the status in the—of the writer and
					the poet in our society. I think you have done a great deal to try to fix it. It
					occurs to me that after some thirty-three years of—I'm
						fifty-two—I started writing poetry when I was about
					eighteen when I was trying to find my way and really always <unclear>felt a sort
						of</unclear> shame in being a poet. Until the other day, a—a man
					of—whom I consider a man of great dignity took me <unclear>to his
						pupils who</unclear> study poetry, because I was a poet. Now, I must say he was
					a Russian who had said <unclear>at</unclear> one time that Russia, the revolution
					killed its soul, and he said this was a great
					tragedy for the country. Now, I think always in extremes of the poet and the
					writer, <inaudible/> <unclear>society,</unclear> and I would suspect that in America we
					<unclear>are more</unclear> conservative in pushing 
					<unclear>against that</unclear> enormous conservatism that is in opposition to the
					complete radicalism of the Russian <inaudible/> <unclear>the opportunities I've
						had</unclear> over the past few days <inaudible/>. This country which is so really
					talented was a radical country, a visionary country, has
					now become crystalized and not writing, so that the poet, I see, from
						my knowledge as a poet, the poets in San Francisco, you
						may laugh at it, their—their manifesto is called "Howl."
					On the other hand, we have our academic—so-called academic poets who
					are very tame <unclear>because</unclear> they don't howl. They don't know how to
					shriek, and there's no guts in the middle.  <inaudible/> There are a few people,
						very few people, who make the synthesis of the romantic and
						classic, the liberal and conservative <inaudible/>.</u>
				<u who="WF">Yes, I agree with that to an extent. I think that there're times
					when—when the voice has more welcome to shout, to howl, than others,
					but I think that the voice is still shouting and howling even if it's inaudible.
					I'm convinced that—that it would take a great deal more than any
					police state to suppress and destroy the heirs to Dostoevsky and Tolstoy. My
					belief is that they are still writing in Russia. They have to hide it in the
					chimney or under the floor, but they are still producing the books.</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.15" start="00:20:02.58" end="00:21:40.13">
					<head>Unrecognized Artists</head>
					<u who="Q">Yes, well very fortunately
						due to the death of Stalin now, the writers have been
					freed, and there is a great flourishing, and people were writing, people like
					<inaudible/> have been writing, others, <inaudible/> has been writing novels, and
					I—I can't evaluate them, but my friend who knows the Russian
					literature says they are distinguished works. <inaudible/> But there is another
						<unclear>sad</unclear> fact that in post-revolution Russia
						<unclear>the—the artist has</unclear> <inaudible/> but the critics—I think the critics are
					lacking <inaudible/> have never honored their poets, their
						visionaries <inaudible/> are always<inaudible/></u>
				<u who="WF">Well, maybe so. I'm—I'm not too convinced that that has hurt
					the—the writing, though, has hurt the poet.</u>
				<u who="Q">No, I suppose <unclear>the poetry</unclear> <inaudible/>.</u>
					<u who="WF">It would be—it would be pleasanter if he did get recognition and were a—an
						<unclear>integer</unclear>—or a definite integer in
					the—the culture of the country, but—but whether he is or
					not, he's going to continue to—to be a poet and to dedicate his life
					and his breath to being a poet simply because that's what he likes. That's his
					cup of tea.</u>
				<u who="Q">Yes, but it's difficult <inaudible/> the artist needs
					somehow <inaudible/>.</u>
				<u who="WF">Well, yes.
				</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.16" start="00:21:40.12" end="00:23:35.83">
					<head>Modern Dilemma</head>
					
					<u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
				<u who="Q">You surely don't mean that this modern dilemma which you've described so
					well is concerned specifically, for instance, with the poets and artists. Do you
					think <unclear>humans</unclear>—do you think it applies just to the
					creative group of people, or do you think it applies more widely?</u>
				<u who="WF">I think—I would say that—that, of course, it applies to
					everybody, but—but the creative man will suffer from it. The young man
					that—that knows "there's something wrong with what I do—I
					don't know what it is, but I do know there's something wrong." That's because he
					has not the—the perspective of an older person's hindsight to measure
					against. I—yes, I think anyone would be hurt. A—a doctor
					would be a better doctor for being more of a humanitarian, a better lawyer. I
					was thinking more of people who deal with the human spirit. That is, the
					teacher, not the doer, but the teacher, which are men in—in the
					colleges, the—the priests, the—the artists,
					whose—whose craft, whose vocation is—is showing man the
					splendor of his long history, that a—a frail web of—of flesh
					and bone, mostly water, stuck together in a ramshackle world held together by
					electricity which may collapse at any moment, yet somehow he still believes in
					it and still gets fired up enough to—to produce poetic records of man's struggle
					which are still pleasing and still uplift the human hearts five hundred years
					after they were written, done.
				</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.17" start="00:23:37.36" end="00:25:32.37">
					<head>Modernity v Individualism</head>
					<u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner?</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
					<u who="Q"><unclear>I wonder</unclear> what you would say <inaudible/> this current cycle of
						decay <inaudible/>?</u>
				<u who="WF">Well, I don't quite like the word decay. I—as I see it, it was
					because of—of overpopulation maybe and the—the mistakes
					of—that we had made which brought on the wars have compelled people
					to—to coalesce in order to—to get along, to live, that more
					children are being born every year with no provisions to take care of the ones
					that we already have, that the man who insists on being an eccentric and an
					individual is in everybody else's way. He's got to belong to something simply to
					keep the wheels running smooth, which is fine for people to get along, but that
					is bad for the artist, for the man to paint in and compose the music and write
					the poetry.</u>
				<u who="Q">What year <unclear>was it</unclear> around—what year would you
					say this <unclear>period</unclear> began?</u>
				<u who="WF">Oh, around 1912, '13, '14, maybe.</u>
				<u who="Q">In other words, before the First World War?</u>
				<u who="WF">Yes, the seeds of it were implicit in the turn of the century, though
					maybe it began—well, '28, '29, and the collapse of Wall Street. That
					may have been the first milepost of it.  Though it's hard to say just where it
					did begin. I would say that's—was a—a sharp mark to measure from.  Say
					'29 maybe.</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.18" start="00:25:33.00" end="00:27:09.10">
					<head>Art vs Reform</head>
					<u who="Q">Mr. Faulkner?</u>
				<u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
				<u who="Q">After the writer or poet has gotten the howl out of his system,
					what—in what way do you think that he can influence his society to
					become more individualistic?</u>
				<u who="WF">Well, if he's going to put in the time on influencing his society, he
					ain't going to have much time left to be a good poet. <event desc="audience laughter"/> 
					I think that he had better go ahead and—and be a good
					poet and let his influence on society take care of itself, but I think
					he—that he is still got to—to write his poetry about the
					simple fundamental verities of—of the human heart in conflict with
					itself, not in conflict with labor unions, nor with high prices, nor with, "How
					am I going to get a Cadillac when all I've got now is a Mercury." He's got to
					stick to the simple, fundamental things, which are the anguishes and troubles of
					his own aspirations and his failed capability and capacity to—to
					accomplish what he can <unclear>dream</unclear>. That's what the—the—the 
					music, the poetry is about. It's—it's not about economics nor
					belonging to groups nor liberal movements nor improving mankind because the
					artist really don't really give a damn about mankind. He's too busy. He's busy being an
					artist, writing poetry or composing music, taking pictures.</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.19" start="00:27:09.11" end="00:27:51.05">
					<head>Art and Environment</head>
					<u who="FS">Mr. Faulkner?</u>
				<u who="WF">Yes, sir?</u>
				<u who="FS">I'm <unclear>going</unclear> to ask a question which you may think
					trivial. Suppose we had the ideal society, economic society, where everybody had
					leisure and comfort and all the Cadillacs we could use. What would that do, if
					anything, to literature <unclear>or</unclear> poetry?</u>
				<u who="WF">I think the poet would still be a poet. He'd prefer to be a poet than to
					have the Cadillac. There may be a culture which would compel him to have that
					Cadillac, but he would be a poor Cadillac owner just like he'd be a poor doctor
					or lawyer because he's going to be a poet first. <event desc="audience laughter"/>
				</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.20" start="00:27:53.20" end="00:30:16.05">
					<head>Snopes v Holden Caulfield</head>
					<u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
				<u who="Q"><unclear>Could you</unclear> compare Wall Street Panic Snopes and Holden
					Caulfield, please? What advantages or qualities are there in Wall Street Panic
					that Holden Caulfield has not now and never did have?</u>
				<u who="WF">Wall Street Panic knew where he wanted to go. He knew that he could get
					there provided he observed a few of the rules of the game, which he did, and he
					got there. I think that Wall Street Panic wasn't really a Snopes, that probably,
					actually, he was not a Snopes, that—that his—his father's
					mama may have done a little extra-curricular night work, <event desc="audience laughter"/> and that he really wasn't a Snopes. He was
					a—a—more of a simple human being than the other Snopes were.
					But he—he wanted to be independent, wanted to make money, but he had
					rules about how he was going to do it. He wanted to make money by simple
					industry, the old rules of—of working hard and saving your pennies, not by taking
					advantage of anybody.</u>
				<u who="Q">Could you contrast him please with <inaudible/> to Holden Caulfield in <hi rend="italic">Catcher in the Rye</hi>?</u>
				<u who="WF">Well, I think that they were completely different. There's almost no
					grounds that—that they would meet on. That Caulfield was a—a
					sensitive young man that wanted to love man and couldn't find him. Wall Street
					Panic Snopes was going to get along with man, but he didn't especially love man
					nor—nor did he have anything against man. He simply wanted
					to—to make a little money. He wanted success in—in his own
					terms of—of hard work, industry, which Caulfield didn't. Caulfield
					wanted to love man, to be accepted by mankind, and he couldn't because in his
					sensitive terms, mankind wasn't there when he tried to touch it.</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.21" start="00:30:16.06" end="00:31:46.07">
					<head>Holden's Tragedy</head>
					<u who="JC">Mr. Faulkner, you said earlier
					that Holden Caulfield's tragedy was the fact that mankind wasn't there or that
					Holden Caulfield didn't think he was there?</u>
				<u who="WF">He wasn't there.</u>
				<u who="JC">I sometimes thought the tragedy of Holden Caulfield was that he did not
					fall, in a way, that if he fell off into humanity he might've found humanity.</u>
				<u who="WF">Well, he would have to have been tougher than he was. If he had been
					tougher than that, there wouldn't have been any story in the first place, but
					his—his story was an—an intelligent, very sensitive young
					man who was in this—this day and time was an anachronism, was almost
					an obsolescence, trying to cope with and struggle with—with the
					present-day world, which he was not fitted for. When—he didn't want
					money. He didn't want position, anything. He just wanted to find man and wanted
					something to love, and he couldn't. There was nothing there. The nearest he came
					to it was his sister who was a child, and—and though she tried to love
					him, she couldn't understand his problem. The only other human beings he ran
					into, he had preconceptions to doubt, the—the teacher which could've
					helped him, and he suddenly began to suspect the teacher's motives.</u></div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio23_1.22" start="00:31:46.08" end="00:33:42.10">
					<head>Holden and Quentin</head>
					<u who="B">Sir, this sounds an awful lot like
					a novel called <hi rend="italic">The Sound and the Fury</hi>,
					<unclear>with</unclear> Quentin Compson wanting to love people and the same sort
					of relationship with his sister.</u>
				<u who="WF">I don't quite agree with you. I don't believe that—that
					Quentin and Holden were very much alike in—except in being a little too sensitive
					and coming from a somewhat similar background of—of people that
					were—were over-intelligent but incapable of—of any strength
					of—of mutual affection and tenderness, which, as I got it,
					was—was Holden's home.</u>
				<u who="AKD">Mr. Faulkner, Holden wasn't grown up, and Quentin was grown up. He was
					holding onto something.  <inaudible/>  He was a case of arrested
					development, and Holden was a case of <inaudible/>. Isn't that true?</u>
				<u who="WF">Yes, sir, there was that difference.</u>
				<u who="AKD">I don't know whether I read Quentin right or not, but he was holding onto
					an ideal, wasn't he, sir?</u>
				<u who="WF">Yes, sir.</u>
					<u who="AKD">That—that simply could not be lived up to in his terms.</u>
				<u who="WF">Yes, that's right. That couldn't have been lived up to in any time
					maybe. But Holden Caulfield was simply looking for something which should be
					everybody's right, not only a privilege, but everybody's right, to find mankind
					and—and love mankind and be accepted into mankind, and he couldn't,
					because mankind, as I tried to say in my paper <inaudible/> <event desc="end of recording"/></u></div2>
				</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>