<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-tei-spoken/uva-tei-spoken.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-tei-spoken/uva-tei-spoken.dtd">
]>
<TEI.2 id="wfaudio30_1_2clip">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Transcript of clip from audio recordings wfaudio30_1 and wfaudio30_2</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription</resp>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI P4 XML markup in conformance with the uva-tei-spoken DTD</resp>
                    <name>AEL Data</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="digital audio filename">wfaudio30_1_2clip</idno>
                <idno type="analog tape">None</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <recordingStmt>
                    <recording type="audio"> </recording>
                </recordingStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <person>
                    <p id="Q">Unidentified participant</p>
                </person>
                <person>
                    <persName id="WF">William Faulkner</persName>
                </person>
                
            </particDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date value="1958-05-12">12 May 1958</date>
                    <locale>Representatives from Other Colleges</locale>
                    <name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name type="city">Charlottesville, Virginia</name>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="event1">
                <head>DATE: 12 May 1958</head>
                <head>OCCASION: Representatives from Other Colleges</head>
                <head>This clip was created by splicing the end of T-145a and the beginning of T-145b together.</head>
                
                <div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio30_1_2.1" start="00:00:00.00" end="00:02:09.55">
                    <head>Spliced clip</head>
                    <u who="WF">Yes, ma'am.</u>
                    <u who="Q">I'm curious as to when—why <inaudible/> I wonder how the modern
                        writer justifies using violence in his work. <unclear>I've been struck by it and
                            sometimes upset by it.</unclear></u>
                    <u who="WF">I think that is one of the tools. That's a particular saw, hammer that the
                        particular carpenter feels he can do most with, that he might not like the
                        violence either. It's simply because he does not have a better tool to show man
                        in his tragic or comic moments inside the predicament. That is, the dramatic
                        story is, man is faced—the frail, fragile creature of flesh and bone,
                        mostly water, in a ramshackle universe stuck together with electricity, faced
                        with problems which are usually bigger than he is. The story is, does he face
                        it? Does it lick him? Or does he beat it? Or if it licks him, does he get beaten
                        to his knees still, as Hemingway says, "Looking good." That, I think,
                        is—is what anyone writes about. It's man that is striving to be braver
                        than he might be, more honest than he might be, to be compassionate.</u>
                    <u who="Q">And it's so important in twentieth century, more than in other centuries <inaudible/>
                        <unclear>to write about this</unclear>?</u>
                    <u who="WF">Well, no, it's always been important. I think that's what makes man
                        endure and what will cause him to endure, that he is capable of wanting to be
                        brave and to be honest and to be compassionate, and he will last. He's outlasted
                        his dinosaurs. He'll outlast his atom bomb. My belief is that the last sound on
                        earth, when this earth is a red rock freezing, will be two folks building an
                        airship and fussing about where they're going next. <event desc="audience laughter"/> Man is all right. You can't beat him. No,
                        there'll be three. The other one will be writing a book about it. <event desc="audience laughter"/>
                    </u>                
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>