<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-tei-spoken/uva-tei-spoken.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-tei-spoken/uva-tei-spoken.dtd">
]>
<TEI.2 id="wfaudio11_1">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Transcript of audio recording wfaudio11_1</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Creation of electronic transcription</resp>
					<name/>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI P4 XML markup in conformance with the uva-tei-spoken DTD</resp>
					<name>AEL Data</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
				<idno type="digital audio filename">wfaudio11_1</idno>
				<idno type="analog tape">T-123c</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<recordingStmt>
					<recording type="audio"> </recording>
				</recordingStmt>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<particDesc>
				<person>
					<persName id="RD">Robert Davis</persName>
				</person>
				<person>
					<persName id="WF">William Faulkner</persName>
				</person>
				<person>
					<persName id="AH">Atcheson Hench</persName>
				</person>
				<person>
					<persName id="ES">Edward Stephenson</persName>
				</person>
				<person>
					<persName id="B">Joseph Blotner</persName>
				</person>
				<person>
					<p id="E">Engineer</p>
				</person>
				<person>
					<persName id="G">Frederick Gwynn</persName>
				</person>
				<person>
					<p id="Q">Unidentified participant</p>
				</person>
			</particDesc>
			<settingDesc>
				<setting>
					<date value="1957-05-07">7 May 1957</date>
					<locale>University Radio Show</locale>
					<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
					<name type="city">Charlottesville, Virginia</name>
				</setting>
			</settingDesc>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="event1">
				
				<head>DATE: 7 May 1957</head>
				<head>OCCASION: University Radio Show</head>
				<head>TAPE: T-123c</head><head>LENGTH: 31:47</head>
				
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.1" start="00:00:00.00" end="00:02:06.47">
					<head>Warmup</head>
					<u who="AH">
						<inaudible/> road shows, as he says.</u>
					<u who="B"> Well, we haven't heard from the agent, the
							circuit.  Right now there are none planned. </u>
					<u who="E"> Just a little bit there. If you can lean in, Mr. Faulkner, without
						hurting it. <event desc="laughter"/>
						<inaudible/></u>
					<u who="AH"> This is to remind us of our names. Wait a minute. I haven't got
						Blotner down there.</u>
					<u who="B"> Yeah, you have.</u>
					<u who="ES"> But not—not—</u>
					<u who="B"> No.</u>
					<u who="Q"> Why don't you just turn it around?</u>
					<u who="WF">Just write his name on a piece of paper and pin it to him. <event
						desc="laughter"/></u>
					<u who="Q"> Like they do at conventions.</u>
					<u who="G">Preferably on the inside.</u>
					<u who="AH"> 'Cause every now and then one of us just goes blind as far as the
						words are concerned—I mean names are concerned. Have you ever forgotten your
						own name, Joe?</u>
					<u who="B">No, but I've heard another announcer do it.</u>
					<u who="AH"> You did?</u>
					<u who="B">He said, "And your announcer has been"—<event desc="laughter"/>. He
						just turned on the record.</u>
					<u who="E">Mr. Faulkner, do you think you will be sitting forward like that most
						of the time?</u>
					<u who="WF">I can sit wherever you want me to.</u>
					<u who="E">Well,that—that'll be fine. Just about like that. I think Mr. Hench
						has a slightly louder voice <unclear>and so it should balance it out</unclear>.</u>
					<u who="AH">Does he want to try us out?</u>
					<u who="E"> Yes, sir.  In just a second.</u>
					<u who="AH">Alright. Well, this is cheating, in a way, to do these two fifteen
						minuteses and then to say that "Last week"—it's going to be awful hard— <event
							desc="laughter"/></u>
					<u who="ES">You just lie one thing after another, don't you?
						A terrible liar.</u>
					<u who="AH">Who, me?</u>
					<u who="ES">Mmhmm.</u>
					<u who="AH">Well, how is this—how does this sound? Is that alright? And Mr.
						Faulkner you could say, "Eeny meeny miney mo" or anything else.</u>
					<u who="WF">If I know it, I will. <event desc="laughter"/> You mean the rest of
						it or just "eeny meeny miney mo"?</u>
					<u who="AH"><inaudible/> just testing your voice.</u>
					<u who="E">All right.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.2" start="00:02:06.48" end="00:04:43.17">
					<head>Blend Words</head>
					<u who="ES">Is that all right now? Can anyone tell me where these wonderful
						blend words in "Spotted Horses" are? "Sward" is one of them I remember. Can
						you hear me all right?</u>

					<u who="RD">I haven't read "Spotted Horses" in a year, so I won't be able to
						tell you about that one.</u>
					<u who="B">I'm not sure I know where they are, Steve.</u>
					<u who="ES">Did you make up that word "sward" or is that something you've
						heard?</u>
					<u who="WF">No, no, that's the way they pronounce it.</u>
					<u who="AH">Joe, Joe.</u>
					<u who="B">One, two, three, four, five. How's that? Does that—is that alright? A
						little more volume? Do you need some more gain?</u>
					<u who="E">Down a little.</u>
					<u who="B">One two, three, four, five. How's that? Okay?</u>
					<u who="E">That's all right."</u>
					<u who="AH">What'd you say, <unclear>game?</unclear></u>
					<u who="B">
						Gain, gain.
					</u>
					<u who="AH">Oh, gain.</u>
					<u who="B">The engineer rides the gain. He picks it up or
						cuts it down.</u>
					<u who="AH">Oh. <event desc="laughter"/></u>
					<u who="E">The opening is already on the tape, so any time you gentlemen feel
						ready. </u>
					<u who="AH">Are you going to set the clock for us?</u>
					<u who="E">It is set, and we'll just start it.<inaudible/> we'll give you twelve
						and a half minutes, <unclear>sir</unclear>, for the first show.</u>
					<u who="AH"><unclear>He's got some signals</unclear> he doesn't understand. Oh, yes.</u>
					<u who="E">No rattling of elbows, then.</u>
					<u who="AH">No rattling of elbows then. Let's not pound the table for once,
						shall we?<event desc="laughter"/> I pounded the table once, and Steve
						pounded the table once in excitement.</u>
					<u who="E">It hasn't been done since.</u>
					<u who="AH">I mustn't say <unclear>"uh-huh"</unclear>.</u>
					<u who="B">Yesterday I opened that door, and it sounded like a pistol shot when
						it hit the wall in <unclear>that basement</unclear>.</u>
					<u who="AH">It did.</u>
					<u who="B"><inaudible/> jumped.</u>
					<u who="RD">They ought to do something about ventilating that room. It was
						awfully hot in there.</u>
					<u who="B">It was getting pretty stuffy.</u>
					<u who="ES">Blowers weren't on, were they?</u>
					<u who="AH">I don't know.</u>
					<u who="ES">It's supposed to be air conditioning with blowers, but I
							don't think they were on.</u>
					<u who="RD">Mr. Stephenson, can I have a match, sir?</u>
					<u who="ES">Sure.</u>
					<u who="RD">Thank you.</u>
					<u who="B">Well, do you have—</u>
					<u who="RD">Would you like to light it, Mr. Faulkner?</u>
					<u who="WF">No, thank you, sir. I'm just about smoked out.</u>
					<u who="B">Do you have a lot of eloquent, impromptu comments there, Atch? Typed
						out?</u>
					<u who="AH">I got my—my stuff. I— </u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.3" start="00:04:53.40" end="00:05:48.25">
					<head>Introduction</head>
					<u who="AH">Today as our special guest we have with us the American novelist
						William Faulkner, author-in-residence at the University of Virginia this
						semester. We are indeed fortunate to have him with us. Also around our table
						today are our regular panel members Mr. Edward Stephenson and Mr. Robert
						Davis. As—and, as another special panel member today, we have Mr. Joseph
						Blotner, of the English Department. And our subject today is Mr. Faulkner's
						dialect. And I suppose we might as well lay on the table one plain fact, one
						simple fact at first, that it is Mississippi dialect. Isn't it, Mr.
						Faulkner?</u>
					<u who="WF">As far as I know. I wouldn't limit it to Mississippi, though. I
						think I've heard this same dialect in Arkansas, Louisiana, Alabama. And I
						imagine, in time, I'll hear it here in Virginia.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.4" start="00:05:48.41" end="00:06:11.17">
					<head>Mississippi v Southern Dialect</head>
					<u who="AH">Would you hear the same words, all the same vocabulary?</u>
					<u who="WF">I wouldn't be surprised. <unclear>I probably would.</unclear></u>
					<u who="AH">Do you think so, Mr. Stephenson?</u>
					<u who="Q">Well, I—</u>
					<u who="ES">Well, the southern dialect—of course, I'm a native of
						Georgia, and I read many things in Mr. Faulkner's writings that are familiar
						to me. I run across some things that are not. I expect there might be some
						small differences.</u>
					<u who="WF">Oh, yes, there would be small differences.</u>
					<u who="ES">But it is a southern dialect.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.5" start="00:06:11.10" end="00:06:51.58">
					<head>Types of Dialect</head>
					<u who="ES"> By the way, Mr. Faulkner, how many
						different types of dialect do you try to distinguish? Now I notice, of
						course, the difference between the speech of the Negroes and the poor white
						trash. Are there any other distinctions that you try to make?</u>
					<u who="WF">I would say there are three. The—the dialect, the diction, of the
						educated, semi-metropolitan white southerner, the dialect of the—of the
						hill, backwoods southerner, and the dialect of the Negro—four, the dialect
						of the Negro who has been influenced by the northern cities, who has been to
						Chicago and Detroit.</u>
					<u who="ES">Four different dialects?</u>
					<u who="WF">Four.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.6" start="00:06:51.56" end="00:07:18.14">
					<head>Dialect and Status</head>
					<u who="AH">Do you find that your characters change their dialect as they
						improve in financial status?</u>
					<u who="WF">Not always. Sometimes. The ones that are—that take up snobbery
						easily, yes, they will change their dialect, and young people have an
						aptitude for changing their dialect, like a chameleon does.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.7" start="00:07:17.83" end="00:08:04.98">
					<head>Suption</head>
					<u who="AH">By the way, a friend of yours asked me to ask you a question today.
						He said that Flem Snopes doesn't smoke, but he'll chew a little tobacco till
						all the "suption" is out of it. He wanted me to ask you if you coined that
						word "suption."</u>
					<u who="WF">No, no. Did you ever hear of that in Georgia, Mr. Stephenson?</u>
					<u who="ES">No, I'm not familiar with that.</u>
					<u who="WF">Well, it means nourishment. Now I don't know that I—</u>
					<u who="AH">It doesn't mean juice?</u>
					<u who="WF">Well, nourishment. There's suption in meat, in bread, it's—I think
						it's more nourishment than juice.</u>
					<u who="RD">The goodness. We'd—I think we'd say he got the goodness out of
						it.</u>
					<u who="WF">Goodness, yes, that's right.</u>
					<u who="ES">Have you heard that in Alabama, Mr. Davis?</u>
					<u who="RD">Suption? I don't think I've heard of suption but—</u>
					<u who="ES">Maybe it's a Mississippi word.</u>
					<u who="WF">When chewing gum is no longer sweet, the suption is gone.</u>
					<u who="ES">Mmhmm.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.8" start="00:08:05.69" end="00:09:05.10">
					<head>Pussel-gutted</head>
					<u who="AH">Mr. Faulkner, I had—have down here on a list several words that I
						would like to ask you about. It's—one is the word "pussel-gutted." You spoke
						about Jewel calling his horse "pussel-gutted," and that was in mock
						affection. And then in another place Peabody—this is in, by the way, in <hi
							rend="italic">As I Lay Dying</hi>—Peabody has "pussel-gutted" himself
						eating cold greens. I suppose that means make yourself flabby.</u>
					<u who="WF">Bloated, yes.</u>
					<u who="ES">That's a Georgia term. I know that term.</u>
					<u who="AH">Is there a plant that you're—that is behind that figure of speech,
						pussel?</u>
					<u who="WF">No.</u>
					<u who="AH">There's a plant in Virginia called <unclear>pussley</unclear>, and
						I thought maybe it was the same thing. It's a hideous plant, an ugly plant.
						It gets full of water.</u>
					<u who="WF">It could derive from that. I don't know. I've heard it all my life.
						It means someone that is bloated, that has a tremendous belly that he
						shouldn't have.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.9" start="00:09:05.11" end="00:10:01.85">
					<head>Kernal v Cunnel</head>
					<u who="ES">May I come back for a moment to this distinction between the speech
						of the Negroes and of the—of what used to be called the poor white trash. In
						your short story "Wash," Mr. Faulkner, when Wash is talking about Colonel
						Sutpen, he call—you spell it K-E-R-N-E-L, when the Negroes are talking you
						spell it C-U-N-N-E-L. Is that supposed to be "Kernal' that Wash says, and
						"Cunnel" that the Negroes say. In other words, Negroes drop the "r."</u>
					<u who="WF">That's correct.</u>
					<u who="ES">That's the idea.</u>
					<u who="WF">That's correct. And the—what we call the redneck white man has a
						hard "r."</u>
					<u who="ES">He has the—</u>
					<u who="WF">He says "fur" for far. He says "far" for fire.</u>
					<u who="ES">Yes.</u>
					<u who="WF">The Negro don't have the hard "r."</u>
					<u who="ES">I assumed that that was the purpose of that. Now if Colonel Sutpen
						or one of his—upper class characters was speaking, then you just use the
						conventional spelling, which really would be rather like Wash's
						pronunciation, though not as hard on "r"'s.</u>
					<u who="WF">That's right, it's between—</u>
					<u who="ES">But the—between Wash and the Negroes, "Kernal" versus "Cunnel."</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.10" start="00:10:02.45" end="00:10:37.56">
					<head>Peakling</head>
					<u who="AH">May I ask you about another word that I noticed, and that's the word
							"peakling."  You said about Jewel, or rather in
						connection with Jewel it was said, "I told them that's why ma always whipped
						him and petted him more. Because he was "peakling" around the house.</u>
					<u who="WF">That's probably a—a corruption or contraction between "puny" and
						"weakly." Just like the contraction or corruption between "mist" and
						"drizzle" becomes "mizzle."</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.11" start="00:10:37.57" end="00:11:17.49">
					<head>Ay for Yes</head>
					<u who="RD">Mr. Faulkner, I noticed that Vernon and Uncle Billy, in <hi
							rend="italic">As I Lay Dying, </hi>often say "ay" for "yes." I wondered
						if that was—if that was common or whether it was just characteristic of the
						older generation?</u>
					<u who="WF">That is common among the older people whose ancestry was
						Scottish.</u>
					<u who="RD">Oh, yes, sir.</u>
					<u who="WF">They came to the mountains of North Carolina, then they came to the
						mountains of Virginia, then they came to the hills of Mississippi, and they
						kept their old ways. They would say to "red up" a room, just as you hear in
						Scotland—means to—to clean a room, to make the beds, sweep.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.12" start="00:11:17.60" end="00:11:32.18">
					<head>Beholden</head>
					<u who="AH">Is the same thing true about "beholden"? I'm "beholden" to you.</u>
					<u who="WF">Now would that be Scottish or is that Old English?</u>
					<u who="AH">Well, I suppose it's English and Scottish.</u>
					<u who="WF">Well, yes. That's right.</u>
					<u who="AH">"Red" is certainly Scottish. You're right there.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.13" start="00:11:33.05" end="00:12:16.90">
					<head>Spelling Dialect</head>
					<u who="ES">I'd like to make a point about the importance of knowing the
						author's speech in interpreting his dialect spellings. Now Thomas Nelson
						Page, for instance, when he wants to represent an Old Virginia Negro who
						says "cawn't," will spell that sometimes C-A-R-N-T. And I noticed you've done
						the same thing in "Wash." When the old Negro woman is talking to Colonel
						Sutpen, she says "Yes, mawster," and you spell it M-A-R-S-T-E-R. Now we
						should interpret that "mawster" rather than "master", but it isn't "marster,"
						is it?</u>
					<u who="WF">No.</u>
					<u who="ES">It's "moster." And the "ar" spelling then, since we know that you
						are from a part of the country—and you yourself drop the "r" after a vowel,
						then the "ar" can be a symbol for the sound "aw."</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.14" start="00:12:17.00" end="00:12:58.19">
					<head>Winder</head>
					<u who="RD">I suppose, Mr. Faulkner, that'd be the same thing as when Dilsey
						says, "winda," and you spell it W-I-N-D-E-R. That she says "winda," rather
						than "winder."</u>
					<u who="WF">That's right. There's no "r."</u>
					<u who="RD">But now the backwoodsman would say "winder."</u>
					<u who="WF">That's right.</u>
					<u who="RD">Wouldn't he?</u>
					<u who="WF">"Winder."</u>
					<u who="RD">"Winder."</u>
					<u who="ES">And then you'd have a problem because you'd have to spell it the
						same way if you wanted to represent it in dialect, wouldn't you? That'd be a
						problem for the author to worry about there.</u>
					<u who="WF">I should say, being a Mississippian, I would probably put two r's on
						it.</u>
					<u who="ES">That's what Page does, by the way—no not Page, but James Russell
						Lowell in his "Bigelow Papers" when he wants to represent—in certain parts
						of New England where they have a very hard "r," he puts two "r"'s. That's
						the same thing he does.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.15" start="00:12:58.07" end="00:13:08.49">
					<head>Aguer</head>
					<u who="AH">Is that—is it the same way with that disease that I saw somewhere?
						A-G-U-E-R. An "aga"? Is that right? "Aga."</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes, that's right.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.16" start="00:13:10.44" end="00:13:53.45">
					<head>Ara v Ary</head>
					<u who="ES">What did you mean, Mr. Faulkner, in—I'm not quite sure how you
						intended this to be pronounced—I know the word, but this particular spelling
						of it. Wash says, "if you was A-R-A other man." "Ary other man. Or
						"ara."</u>
					<u who="WF">That's right, "ara."</u>
					<u who="ES">"Ara."</u>
					<u who="WF">"Ara" or "nara."</u>
					<u who="ES">Mmhmm.</u>
					<u who="RD">"Ara." I remember in Alabama, where I lived sort of back in the
						hills myself, and it was "ary" back there, rather than "ara." Funny—</u>
					<u who="AH">"Ary."</u>
					<u who="RD">"Ary." U-huh.</u>
					<u who="AH">And "nary."</u>
					<u who="RD">"Nary."</u>
					<u who="ES">You know that may be an example of of over-correction, just like in
						the mountains when the name Andy becomes "Anda" sometimes, and Naomi becomes
						"Naoma."</u>
					<u who="RD">Or it may be—it may be the—the mountain speech coming down into
						Northern Alabama there.</u>
					<u who="ES">Might be.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.17" start="00:13:53.87" end="00:14:31.05">
					<head>Awry and Ory</head>
					<u who="AH">Mr. Faulkner, how do you pronounce these words: "A-W-R-Y haired" and
						"A-W-R-Y feathered."</u>
					<u who="WF">Awry.</u>
					<u who="AH">Awry.</u>
					<u who="WF">That's what I was trying to spell.</u>
					<u who="AH">I see. Have you ever heard the pronunciation "ory" haired?</u>
					<u who="WF">Not in Mississippi—</u>
					<u who="AH">"Ory" feathered"?</u>
					<u who="B">Is that at all similar to <unclear>"ory eyed"</unclear>? Or does that
						refer to another condition or pronunciation.</u>
					<u who="AH">I think it is. I think it is.</u>
					<u who="WF">Very likely is, but I never heard "ory" applied to anything except
						"eye."</u>
					<u who="B">Mmmhmm.  That's the only usage I know.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.18" start="00:14:31.04" end="00:15:29.09">
					<head>Dog v Dawg</head>
					<u who="ES">I want to ask Mr. Faulkner—ask you Mr. Faulkner why once you spell
						the word dog D-A-W-G for Wash. It seems to me that I don't approve of that
						spelling. That doesn't really differentiate Wash from any of the other
						characters. Wouldn't they all say "dawg"? Don't you say "dawg"? Doesn't
						everybody in Mississippi say "dawg."</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes, the reason for that is that someone has said southerners don't
						read books; they write books. And I think that when the southerner writes
						deliberately spelled dialect, he is writing not for the man that calls "dog"
						"dawg," but for the man that calls "dog" "dog."</u>
					<u who="ES">But "dawg"—"dawg" is very general all over the country. Of course in
						some parts of the Midwest people do say "dog." But in New England and the
						South, and a large part of the rest of the country D-O-G is "dawg"</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes, but these people would speak with a—even more flatness than
						that. It would be "Dawg."</u>
					<u who="AH">Stretched out.</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.19" start="00:15:29.08" end="00:16:42.19">
					<head>Hit for It</head>
					<u who="ES">Well another—another point I'd like to ask you about. In the use of
						"hit" which I'm familiar with in Georgia. It's an old form that's survived.
						But it seems to me, at least in Georgia, the distinction is this. In an
						unstressed, where the—where the syllable would not be accented—for instance,
						you could hardly say—if you wanted to say "Move it over thar," you—it would
						be hard say "move hit over thar." But if you said, "Hit don't make no
						difference"—or—when it's stressed, it would be "hit." But I notice you use it
						rather indiscriminately whether it would be in a stress position or not in a
						stress position. I think—I think you were careless in that regard.</u>
					<u who="WF">Perhaps so, but I think I have heard it used—sometimes the same man
						will say "move hit yonder" or "move it yonder."</u>
					<u who="AH">And "make it now" and "make hit now."</u>
					<u who="WF">That's right, the same—</u>
					<u who="AH">More deliberation.</u>
					<u who="WF">Well, I don't know. It's—he probably is not aware himself. At
						one time he puts an <inaudible/> and the next time he drops it.</u>
					<u who="B">I should think his—the speed with which he spoke or the emotion—</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes, has a lot to do with it.</u>
					<u who="B">That might even determine which spelling—</u>
					<u who="ES">For instance, here's one. Wash says, "You make hit right," and you
						spell it H-I-T, which—but again, he says, "Hit don't need no ticket."</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.20" start="00:16:42.18" end="00:17:11.18">
					<head>Fragment</head>
					<u who="RD">Mr. Faulkner, one thing that I'd like to get in 
						I've wondered how you do it. Just how you go about it. I see some every now
						again, some of these words that I think are—are brilliant. Luster, I
						remember, in the end of <hi rend="italic">The Sound and the Fury</hi>, says—
							<event desc="recording is interrupted by seventeen seconds of music"
						/></u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.21" start="00:17:11.97" end="00:17:28.00">
					<head>Fragment</head>
					<u who="RD"><inaudible/> in our memory I should think.</u>
					<u who="AH">Do you ever create these things?</u>
					<u who="WF">Probably.</u>
					<u who="ES">He doesn't mean to, though.</u>
					<u who="WF">No, I don't deliberately, but I—probably I have corrupted words
							 on my own ticket.</u>
					<u who="ES">To get a good result.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.22" start="00:17:27.94" end="00:18:03.76">
					<head>Close</head>
					<u who="AH">We've enjoyed being with you for the past fifteen minutes for this
						chat. There is much more on the subject that we could say, but our time has
						run out on us again. However, we cordially invite you to be in our listening
						audience next week at this same time, when Mr. Faulkner will again be in
						our—will be our special guest. Joining us around the table today were Mr. Ed
						Stephenson, Mr. Joseph Blotner, and Mr. Robert Davis. Our special guest for
						this program was Mr. William Faulkner. This is Atcheson Hench thanking you
						for joining our discussion today and inviting you to listen again next week
						at this time for another chat on some aspect of the language we speak.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.23" start="00:18:04.36" end="00:18:18.19">
					<head>Break, 1</head>
					<u who="G">
						<event desc="cough"/>
					</u>
					<u who="RD">Have you been waiting all that time to cough, Mr. Gwynn?</u>
					<u who="WF">Now's the time for Mr. Hench to get up and do this again. <event
							desc="laughter"/></u>
					<event desc="laughter"/>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.24" start="00:18:18.31" end="00:18:32.17">
					<head>Break, 2</head>
					<u who="E">You may stretch your muscles just a moment just while we switch tapes
						and then we'll continue again as though we never stopped.</u>
					<u who="AH">Well wasn't it brilliant?</u>
					<u who="G">That worked very well.</u>
					<u who="B">You were great, Hench.  <event desc="laughter"/></u>
					
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.25" start="00:18:34.24" end="00:18:55.17">
					<head>Elefunk</head>
					<u who="AH">Oh dear. You know I—you speaking about <unclear>"elefunk"</unclear>.
						I think that's one of those rebuildings to suit what the man probably thinks
						it ought to be, like <unclear>"plathform"</unclear> instead of "platform."
						Though what <unclear>"funk"</unclear>—"elefunk" would be I wouldn't have any idea. But he's got
						some notion in there.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.26" start="00:18:57.47" end="00:19:36.69">
					<head>Jaybirds and Hell</head>
					<u who="RD">There's something I've wondered about, and I don't guess 
						we can ask it on this program, so I'll just ask it
						now. I remember Luster says—he chunks some rocks at some jaybirds, and he
						says, "Git on back to hell, whar you belong at. 'Taint Monday yit." I
						wondered what that superstition—I never heard that superstition—</u>
					<u who="WF">The superstition is that on Friday the jaybirds all go to hell; they
						don't come back till Monday.</u>
					<u who="RD"><inaudible/> around from that Monday until the next Friday.</u>
					<u who="WF">Quite often you never hear a jaybird over the weekend, and the
						superstition is they've gone to hell.</u>
					<u who="B">That's probably what they've done.</u>
					<u who="WF">Sometimes that is where they should go—</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.27" start="00:19:36.70" end="00:20:03.87">
					<head>No more despair</head>
					<u who="B">Gee, there was one that I wanted to ask about. In "Spotted Horses,"
						when Armstid's wife tells how badly off they are and says that "He aint no
						more despair than to spend four dollars for a horse." I know what she means,
						but I've just never heard those words put together that way before.</u>
					<u who="ES">
						<inaudible/>
						I'm familiar with that.
					</u>
					<u who="B">Are you?</u>
					<u who="WF">It means he has no more shame, no more consideration, for
							our trouble.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.28" start="00:20:17.35" end="00:20:36.43">
					<head>Technical Terms</head>
					<u who="B">I'm glad you didn't use any—any technical terms on us, Steve, like
							 post-vocalic "r."   Stuff like that it was the wrong
						thing to do.</u>
					<u who="ES">I slipped up and did that one time. It was the first program we did then I realized
						that was the wrong thing to do —</u>
					<u who="B">You might just as well use Esperanto.</u>
					<u who="ES">I won't talk about this <inaudible/> vowel then.</u>
					<u who="B">Good.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.29" start="00:20:38.78" end="00:20:51.12">
					<head>Starting Program Two</head>
					<u who="E">Okay? You gentleman ready for—?</u>
					<u who="B">Do you want to reset the clock?</u>
					<u who="AH">I think it does, and that every now and then helps me if I think of
						it.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.30" start="00:20:59.58" end="00:21:30.67">
					<head>Swurge for Surge</head>
					<u who="WF">Did you ever hear of "swurge" for "surge?"</u>
					<u who="ES">No, that was another one I marked in "Spotted Horses." And you
						didn't invent that either. I thought maybe you invented that. It's a
						wonderful term, I think. It conveys the idea beautifully, but—</u>
					<u who="AH">I think I've heard that "w" in certain places. I can't pull one out
						of my head right now. But I think in the mountains up here, in the Blue
						Ridge, I've heard a "w" that gets—</u>
					<u who="ES">It could be. I could see how it happens. It could be the reverse of
						the loss of the "w" in "sword." "Sward."</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.31" start="00:21:37.66" end="00:22:04.04">
					<head>Opening Program Two</head>
					<u who="AH">Today as our special guest again we have with us the American
						novelist Mr. William Faulkner, author-in-residence at the University of
						Virginia this semester. We are indeed fortunate, as we were last week, to
						have him with us. Also around our table today are our special—are our
						regular panel members Mr. Edward Stephenson and Mr. Robert Davis. And as
						another panel member today, we have Mr. Joseph Blotner.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.32" start="00:22:04.88" end="00:22:36.06">
					<head>Hogfish</head>
					<u who="AH">Mr. Faulkner, following up what we said last week, I should like to
						ask you about the meanings of one or two words. By the way, is there a fish
						in Mississippi called a "hog"?</u>
					<u who="WF">No.</u>
					<u who="AH">Then I misunderstood a line. Somewhere I thought you called a fish a
						hog. Maybe—there's no hogfish?</u>
					<u who="WF">No, I think somebody said the catfish the little boy had was as
						bloody as a hog. It's as full of blood as a hog.</u>
					<u who="AH">Oh, I see. </u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.33" start="00:22:36.07" end="00:22:59.84">
					<head>Frailed</head>
					<u who="AH"> What about the word "frailed"? He "frailed him time and
						time." What's that mean?</u>
					<u who="WF">To whip, thrash.</u>
					<u who="ES">It's a variant of flail, isn't it? Yes, I—I know that. It's a
						variant of flail.</u>
					<u who="WF">—but they say "frail."</u>
					<u who="B">You use that, Mr. Davis?</u>
					<u who="RD">No, sir, I never heard that—I don't think. Not frail.</u>
					<u who="ES">Oh, you're too much of a city boy.</u>
					<u who="RD">I guess so.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.34" start="00:23:00.98" end="00:23:50.06">
					<head>Dust-dark and Dust-dawn</head>
					<u who="AH">What about these two that are—that always have interested me:
						"dust-dark" and "dust-dawn." The time of day which is "dust-dark" and
						"dust-dawn."</u>
					<u who="WF">Twilight.</u>
					<u who="AH">What does "dust" mean there?</u>
					<u who="WF">It's "dusk" really.</u>
					<u who="AH">Dusk.</u>
					<u who="WF">But they say "dust." That is, they say "dus-dark" and "dus-dawn."
						They don't say "dusk-dark" and "dusk-dawn."</u>
					<u who="ES">If you all would let me be technical I'd say that's assimilation to
						the following "d." You see—</u>
					<u who="B">Of course.</u>
					<u who="ES"><unclear>The assimilated "d."</unclear></u>
					<u who="AH">Dusky dark? Have you ever, Mr. Stephenson, heard "dusk-dawn," 
						"dusk-dark"?</u>
					<u who="ES">No, I don't know that.</u>
					<u who="RD">But I've heard "dust" for dusk. For the time of day, it's just
						"dust."</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.35" start="00:23:50.87" end="00:24:47.08">
					<head>Kain't and Class</head>
					<u who="ES">Mr. Faulkner, you have—to come back to the story "Wash" again, which
						I read quite recently—you have Wash say "kain't," but you don't represent
						the colonel as saying that. Don't you think he would have said "kaint"
						too?</u>
					<u who="WF">That was to make a distinction between their social position.</u>
					<u who="ES">It's—it's really a sort of faking in a way. I mean I don't mean to
						be nitpicking but—</u>
					<u who="B">Well, don't you think really the—the colonel himself would have been
						conscious of such things as pronunciation and perhaps would have stressed it
						where Colonel Sartoris might not have?</u>
					<u who="WF">I doubt that. It was Wash's flat drawl. The colonel would have said
						"kaint"; Wash would have said "kayint." And the only way I know to do that
						is to spell it slightly different. Wash has a flatter voice than the
						plantation owner—and the master. <unclear>Though they would use the
							same—</unclear></u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.36" start="00:24:47.09" end="00:25:19.03">
					<head>Holler</head>
					<u who="ES">In that same story, Millie says to Wash, "You'll have to
						holler—you'll have to holler louder than that." "Holler," I suppose.
						H-O-L-L-E-R, you spelled it. That comes back to the question we asked last
						week about what would you do with "winder" if you wanted to have one of the
						poor white trash—</u>
					<u who="WF">Well—</u>
					<u who="ES">It's a problem, isn't it. Because now if this were one of the upper
						class characters, H-O-L-L-E-R would represent "holla," But knowing that it's
						Wash's daughter it's going to be "holler."</u>
					<u who="WF">That's right.</u>
					<u who="ES">So we have to know something about the background.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.37" start="00:25:19.04" end="00:26:21.38">
					<head>Figures of Speech</head>
					<u who="AH">Mr. Faulkner, do you—you have—must have an astonishingly retentive
						memory for figures of speech. I noticed you spoke of a coffin "as neat as a
						sewing basket." And the talk of some women as kind of like "bees murmuring
						in a water bucket." Do you—are these phrases that are proverbial in your
						talk—in the talk of people in Mississippi, or do you make these up, or—or
						what? They're delightful phrases.</u>
					<u who="WF">Those, I imagine, the circumstances of the story invent themselves,
						suggest to me. I've never heard them as— <unclear>as
							analogies</unclear>. Simply the circumstances of the story—or the desire
						to describe that the best I can in comprehensible phrases or figures of
						speech.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.38" start="00:26:21.45" end="00:27:29.15">
					<head>Sources of Figures</head>
					<u who="AH">Do you have any idea which kinds of things you like most to use
						figures of speech—make figures of speech out of. Flowers or fish or horses
						or dogs or trees or just—or don't you worry and care less?</u>
					<u who="WF">I would say that the—the—the instant I am involved
						with does the commanding in that.</u>
					<u who="RD">I think one of the most unusual kinds of figures of speech that I've
						noticed—when certain of your characters—certain of your more perceptive
						characters like Benjy in <hi rend="italic">The Sound and the fury </hi>and
						Darl in <hi rend="italic">As I Lay Dying</hi>—their sense of smell seems to
						be very acute. I know Darl says—when it's getting ready to rain he says it
						smells like sulfur. Well, even Quentin in <hi rend="italic">The Sound and
							the Fury</hi> remembers the smell of the honeysuckle and so forth. I—I
						think that's particulary good and it's rather unusual, I think. Because usually that's one
						of the senses—one of the five that's left out so often in writing. It gives
						that added touch of realism to it.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.39" start="00:27:29.10" end="00:28:07.27">
					<head>Christmas Masts</head>
					<u who="AH">Mr. Faulkner, may I ask you if I—if there's something here in
						Mississippi folklore that I missed, not having grown up in Mississippi. Cora
						says, "His face looked like one of these here Christmas masts that had
						been—that had done been buried a while and then dug up." What is a Christmas
						"mast"?</u>
					<u who="WF">Oh, the toy mask, the comic faces that children buy in the—in the
						stores for Halloween and—and Christmas time.</u>
					<u who="Q">And "mast" is really for "mask"?</u>
					<u who="WF">Mask, yes.</u>
					<u who="Q">Just like "dusty" for "dusk."</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes, that's right.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.40" start="00:28:07.23" end="00:28:54.61">
					<head>Bot as Misprint</head>
					<u who="ES">Mr. Faulkner, in "The Bear," here's a word I don't know.  I wonder if you
						can tell me what it means. The word is B-O-T: "The old game crossing over
						which he'd trailed bucks wounded and not wounded and more than once seen
						them anything but wounded bot out of the woods and up and across the
						embankment—" What's that word B-O-T mean? It looks like a verb having to do
						with rapid motion or something of the sort.</u>
					<u who="WF">I would have to see it.</u>
					<u who="ES">Maybe it's a misprint?</u>
					<u who="WF">It is a misprint, yes. There's no such word as that. If it's not a
						misprint for "but" then—</u>
					<u who="ES">"But out of the woods" would make sense. Or could it be "hot out of
						the woods"?</u>
					<u who="WF">That's a good point.</u>
						<u who="ES">Wherever <inaudible/></u>
					<u who="WF">"Hot."</u>
					<u who="ES">"Hot out of the woods."  I see.</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes, I remember. It was hot.</u>
					<u who="ES">"Hot out of the woods."  That's a misprint. </u>
					<u who="WF">Running at top speed. Yes, "hot out of the woods."</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.41" start="00:28:55.90" end="00:29:25.16">
					<head>Chapping</head>
					<u who="AH">Do all—do many people use the word "chapping" for having children.
						Somebody said, "We ain't nigh done chapping yet."</u>
					<u who="WF">That's quite colloquial. You hear that only in the remote hill
						country. People that—that have no—where there are no Negroes and their
						speech is not corrupted by—by Negro inflections and the Negro usage of words.
						That came from Scotland.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.42" start="00:29:25.90" end="00:29:47.68">
					<head>Lawed</head>
					<u who="AH">Is "lawed"—would you say of—the same thing of "lawed." "He should be
						lawed for treating her so." In other words arrested or something.</u>
					<u who="WF">That's <unclear>not all</unclear>—making a verb out of a noun.</u>
					<u who="AH">You did that yourself?</u>
					<u who="WF">No. I've heard that.</u>
					<u who="AH">Oh, I see.</u>
					<u who="WF">That's—I imagine that that's in Georgia and Alabama, too.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.43" start="00:29:47.42" end="00:30:27.22">
					<head>Tongued</head>
					<u who="ES">What does this mean, Mr. Faulkner? Let's see, "They all piled over
						the crest of the hill just in time to see Tomey's Turl a way out across the
						flat almost to the woods and the dogs streaking down the hill and out onto
						the flat. They just tongued once and when they
						came boiling up around Tomey's Turl they looked like they were going to jump
						up and lick him in the face."</u>
					<u who="WF">Another verb made from a noun. They "gave tongue" once.</u>
					<u who="AH">You've never hunted.</u>
					<u who="ES">No, I'm not a hunter.</u>
					<u who="AH">Well, Mr. Faulkner is. He's heard the sound of dogs.</u>
					<u who="WF">That means they were—they were on game. They bayed once, then they
						recognized Tomey's Turl, a friend, so they quit.</u>
					<u who="ES">I see.</u>
					<u who="WF">They just caught up with him to lick his hand, to run along with
						him.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.44" start="00:30:29.08" end="00:30:45.49">
					<head>A Tie-up</head>
					<u who="AH">Mr. Faulkner, what is a tie-up in a barn?</u>
					<u who="WF">That's anything you tie cattle to. It's near a rack for feeding.</u>
					<u who="AH">Oh, I see. A rack or a bar.</u>
					<u who="WF">A hitch or a lead is snapped into the halter—tied to a
						<unclear>bar</unclear>.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.45" start="00:30:46.83" end="00:31:08.79">
					<head>Soopled</head>
					<u who="ES">And another place, Mr. Faulkner, "Black John came out of the trees,
						driving, soopled out flat and level as a hawk." Is that a verb made from the
						adjective "supple"?</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes, they pronounce "supple," "soople."</u>
					<u who="ES">I've heard the pronunciation of the adjective as "soople." This is a
						verb in the past tense, "soopled."</u>
					<u who="WF">Yes, that's right. To—to "soople" is to do something rapid and
							limber.</u>
				</div2>
				<div2 type="dialog" id="wfaudio11_1.46" start="00:31:09.00" end="00:31:44.50">
					<head>Regional Dialects Q</head>
					<u who="AH">Mr. Faulkner, some days ago I remember your saying that you thought
						you could move, say, to a Maine village, a fishing village or a lumbering
						village, and it wouldn't be long before you would be writing about people
						there. Yet I remember yesterday you said that it was the inflection, the
						sound of the words and the dialect that was very much a part of the people
						that you write about. Don't you think that, though you could see stories
						quickly in the lives of this imagined Maine group of people, it would take
						you a long time to get on to their talk, their pronunciation, and so forth?
							<event desc="end of recording"/></u>
				</div2>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
